when a person
begins to contemplate
a nietzsche or if they realize that
every everything they think everything is
everything they think everything is
impermanent
what then is the best investment
for that person what should they do
about it
because a lot of people say well
everything is impermanent
thus nothing matters hmm
i can do whatever i want because it's
it's all going to end
you know this life it's going to end
anyway so it doesn't matter
well then in the face of that anxiety of
nature well if they feel anxiety okay
but a person who is saying oh
not that it doesn't matter what i do
then they won't probably even be feeling
that anxiety
because if you're feeling anxiety
dismissal will not free you from anxiety
you can say nothing matters but you
fulfill anxiety
which is very unpleasant so what do i do
i can keep saying nothing matters but
anxiety is still there so what do i do
so if a person does genuinely has sense
of a nature through anxiety and
the recognition of that non-control and
yeah things will end
and that will affect me well yeah they
need to recognize it exactly
as something something that must be
addressed not like something they must be
not like something they must be
addressed at a root level
not something that they can just find
the answer to and then move on with
their lives because
well those lives out on each other and
that's what they understand me
so in other words they have to take it
seriously not just try to get rid of the
discomfort like
tell me what a nietzsche is tell me what
to do so i get rid of this comfort of
anxiety not so i fully understand whether
not so i fully understand whether
nietzsche is
because you can temporarily get rid of
this comfort anxiety but as i said many
times before
anxiety is a symptom of an existential
issue it's not a problem
so unless you remove the problem these
symptoms will keep coming back up one
way or the other
so things will be reminding you for each
one of the other doesn't matter how much
you're trying to deal with it
so the first thing you do then is take
the buddhist teaching seriously
take the gradual training seriously
don't just try to get rid of the current
pain that bothers you
but recognize your liability to pain as
already being an issue
even if everything is fine now and there
is no anxiety now
there could be anxiety now and things
could not be fine now
so oh well that would affect me thus
recognition of that
is already something that affects you so
you realize this is the level i must
practice so take the gradual training seriously
so take the gradual training seriously
then the presets
the the guarding of the sense doors um
and yeah uh breathing the suttas
studying and getting the more
understanding of what the buddha was
teaching so it's it's it's dealing with anxiety
so it's it's it's dealing with anxiety
dealing with recognition of impermanence
it's uh well it's a life lifelong task
in a sense of
if you're very committed you might do it
quickly but your life will then change
forever as somebody who is understood and each
as somebody who is understood and each
and free from suffering
if you're not doing it quickly if you're
not so committed
it will take you probably a full
lifetime to get closer to it
either way if you if you reckon as you
have to deal with it
your life cannot remain the same as in
life of sensuality carelessness and
everything else
leading up to that point
so don't think anxiety is something oh i
have a problem with anxiety
something's wrong with me let me get rid
of that go back no no it's a symptom of
an underlying problem that shows you
that maybe
you know this life in existence is not
the way you would like to think it is or
that everybody else seems to think it is
because if it was so why are you anxious
essentiality is not
is enough to keep your mind happy
contented peaceful calm why are you not always
peaceful calm why are you not always
happy content to peaceful and harm
so maybe that's not the answer maybe the
way you're engaging the world and the
views you have with the world
maybe that's why i'm anxious maybe my
anxiety is a symptom of that
the things actually are not aligned
and yeah and each is exactly that things
are unhonorable
not yours yet here you are living your
life as you're the master controller of
your body your senses your ownership
people and so on
a complete blatant contradiction and
anxiety every now and then reminds you
of that
so do something about it before it's too
late which is which is what i just described
which is which is what i just described
study the suttas
keep the precipice strictly gradual
training and
yeah it realized that it's a it's it's
something that will one way or the other
it needs to affect your life at the very
basis of your existence because there's not
of your existence because there's not
something you can do in response to this
particular state
and then i go back to my values from
before because there's at least the one common
because there's at least the one common
response is
trying to appreciate everything now that
everything i realized everything is a
niche and everything's impermanent
that's difficult i'll just appreciate it
i'll just
delight in everything right even more
double down
yeah because double down in my
acceptance right
so so if if you then find out that you
have a terminal cancer maybe a week to
live would that appreciation keep you calm
would that appreciation keep you calm
and unaffected and
and fearless in face of death not
suffering would you be able to equally appreciate
would you be able to equally appreciate
and accept that and enjoy enjoy your
chemo and everything else and the
torture you have to go through and you
know seeing your family
sort of grieve over you and while you're
still alive i appreciate every moment i
appreciate every moment it's a blessing
no it's not
yeah life has its blessings but not all
of it is a blessing and that's the
recognition that's what would have said if the life
that's what would have said if the life
is not if the life were only
the life of misery beings would not be
enamored with it
if the life were only life of blessings
and appreciation well beings would not
be disgusted with it
so life is both and you use wisdom to
recognize yeah don't be irrationally averse to
yeah don't be irrationally averse to
everything
there are blessings there are things you
should appreciate
but recognize that it's all within the
nature of things not being
in control and the nature of things
being subject to change in its core
and that is inaccessible to you can't
affect that you can't prevent that
so keeping that in mind then you put
your appreciation in perspective
you don't use appreciation to deal with
the niche you use a niche
to not get careless with your
appreciation and same you use a nietzsche to not get
and same you use a nietzsche to not get
careless with your non-appreciation or a
version so you use a niche wisdom of recognition
so you use a niche wisdom of recognition
of the nature of things
to keep yourself in check but in order
to do that you need to stop trying to
get rid of it through appreciation or
whatever else you might be doing
because that's the only reason we will
be doing it to get rid of this comfort
of it
oh no no no i accept this actually it's
not up to you
like you know the mountains coming to
crush you yes i accept that like
what who are you to even accept that you
have no say
whether you accept or not this is the
inevitable outcome
so you saying that you appreciate and
accept this it's just you trying to
appease yourself
in the face of something you have no
control over
and that's unpleasant but you need to
stop trying to get rid of it
recognize it as a symptom and then
gradual training you're trying to get
control again you're trying to repossess
it exactly
no no i wanted that to happen no you
didn't
nobody wants to happen
so yeah
gradual picking up federal training
gradual development
gradual composing when i say gradual i
don't mean
take it easy i just mean you do need to
do it gradually you need to start in the
level of
virtue and polish unblemished
unbroken virtue so take it seriously the
behavior then from there
you know your speech will become more
wholesome than even your thoughts and
then you will be able to to
to actually withstand
more of the recognition of nature and
anxiety without
having too much pressure of i must deal
with this and then jump
into one view or the other or one action
or the other because it's unbearable to
you the only reason it's unbearable
because to mind is too weak in relation to it
to mind is too weak in relation to it
the mind is too weak because you haven't
been practicing censor strain god in the
sense those
taming the beasts you haven't been doing
that so they're still very powerful
and so how can you then be in control of
them unless you can physically at least
be able to around them
and not let them drag you around
that composure they will be able to face
the anxiety or any other unpleasantness
will be there because you you build the
basis for it
you know how they're facing i know
you're already facing it by not acting
out of it
by not breaking your virtue when you're
anxious you are already facing anxiety
you are doing it
even if it doesn't feel like that that's
the work
not when you think you're doing the work
or not you're surmounted
there you are and then there were there
was basically a monk who practices mind
basically the mind a monk who practices
keeping his mind
unmoved by things they want to move it
and you don't need to seek out things
that want to move it in terms of
temptations and so on
your senses already want to move it all
the time
even if you're just in alone in a cell
without any distraction
so that's the money so removability of
the mind begins
by immovability of behavior
unbroken virtue the aggregate of virtue
you have created the immovable aggregate
of certain non-behavior
i will not behave towards sensuality
towards you know actions of ill will and
so on
and it becomes this solid thing of
certain behavior is not to be done
hasn't been done
you'd accomplish that and that's your
aggregate of virtue you have to bully
refer to it
in the sense that this body is the solid
aggregate well your virtue becomes the
solid aggregate you don't spill over
you don't break through there and that's
exactly the beginning of somali
sila there then you run and find samadhi
sila gives the basis for samadhi on that
basis and that gives the basis for clear
and that gives the basis for clear
seeing on that
personally yeah basis aggregates of
virtue you build that up you build that
up
and stop eroding it stop taking it
conditionally and stop stop sort of thinking it's kind
and stop stop sort of thinking it's kind
of a side thing your practice comes
through the framework of your virtue
no other way